RelaxNG Test

Preliminary instructions

The goal of this test is to create a well-formed Relax NG schema using a XML document that we will supply for you. Here’s how to get started:

Open the XML document at (lilacs_lyrics.xml) in <oXygen/>. You can open it directly from the Internet by hitting Ctrl+u (Windows) or Cmd+u (Mac) in <oXygen/> and then copying and pasting the URL into the Open URL dialog box.

The XML document for which you will be creating a schema is the song Lilacs from Dave Malloy’s musical

Preludes

. You can hear it performed on YouTube (it’s really a very lovely song, so we highly recommend checking it out!).

Use File → Save As in the <oXygen/> menu to save the XML file locally to your computer.

Create a new Relax NG compact syntax document and save it to your computer in the same directory as the XML, making sure that you follow our file-naming conventions, as you would for any assignment in this class.

After you’ve saved both the XML song file and the new Relax NG file, click into the XML file and then use the Document → Schema → Associate Schema menu options to associate your XML with your Relax NG. The schema won’t be valid yet, which means that XML will also show a red square, but after you’re done with this next task, you will have two beautiful green squares.

Your task

Create a Relax NG schema that validates the XML file that we provide. This test is open book, but you can’t receive help from another person. Here are some more details:

You can’t change the XML exceptfor having <oXygen/> add the association line for the schema.

Your schema should make good use of effective comments that 1) guide the reader through the structure of the schema file and 2) explain the reasons behind any design decisions that aren’t self-explanatory. One guideline for explanatory comments is that although the code itself can often communicate what it does (by using self-documenting names), the code can’t explain why you did one thing instead of another. Documenting what isn’t self-explanatory, then, most often means explaining the why.

We recommend developing your schema step by step, using placeholders, as we demonstrated in class. This approach lets you focus on a small part of the functionality at a time, so that if something doesn’t work, you’ll know where to look to fix it.

<oXygen/> cannot validate any part of the XML if you have an invalid schema (that is, if the schema file shows a red square). To work around that limitation and check at least the parts of your schema that you think are correct, you can put a placeholder like text in the content model for the statement you’re stuck on so that the schema will be valid and <oXygen/> can then use it to validate the XML. This is similar to the use of placeholders for incremental development that we describe above. <oXygen/> will reports validation errors in the XML for the items with the placeholder, but at least you’ll be able to verify whether your other schema statements are doing what you think they should do, and you can then come back to the problematic bits later. The point is that you don’t want a single sticking point to keep you from validating at least parts of your XML.

Your schema should be applicable to multiple documents of the same type, and whether that means all songs in this musical or, more broadly, songs from many different musicals is up to you (so document your decision in a comment in your schema!). For example, if you decide that you (hypothetically) want to mark up the lyrics of every song from this musical, Natalya and Rach aren’t the only characters, so consider that when defining attributes in your schema. And we can’t say this often enough: Whatever decisions you make, be sure to document them with a comment.

If you get stuck, feel free to ask a question in the #relax-ng channel in our Slack. Don’t be shy about doing that; if you have a question, it’s likely that someone else will have the same question. We can’t write the schema rules for you, but there’s a lot we can and will do to point you in the right direction.

Answer Key: RelaxNG Test

Sample schema

Your schema does not have to look the same as ours, but one possible schema that could be used for this XML document (and other songs of the same type) could be:

# Schema for Test 02: Relax NG
# 
# Root element
# Generic root element name because applicable to multiple songs
start = song
song = element song { metadata, lyrics }
# 
# METADATA SECTION
# 
# Songs may have titles for both the song itself and the musical
metadata = element metadata { title+, characters, artist, source }
title = element title { type, text }
type = attribute type { "musical" | "song" }
# 
# Characters featured in the song and who they are portrayed by
# Content is character name, performer is attribute
characters = element characters { character+ }
character = element character { actor, text }
actor = attribute actor { text }
# 
# Creator of the musical / source of lyrics
# Assume that the song is the work of a single artist
artist = element artist { text }
source = element source { text }
# 
# LYRIC SECTION
#
# Sections are groups of stanzas
lyrics = element lyrics { (section | direction | toneshift)+ }
toneshift = element toneshift { empty }
# Stage directions
direction =
  element direction {
    mixed { chara* }
  }
# 
# section elements
# a change in tone starts a new section
# a change in speaker, delivery, or action starts a new stanza
section = element section { tone, stanza+ }
tone = attribute tone { "positive" | "negative" | "neutral" }
stanza = element stanza { speaker, delivery, action?, line+ }
# 
# speaker element and attributes
# action (optional) is activity performed while singing the stanza
# speaker is defined as text, rather or-group fixed values, to accomodate other shows 
speaker = attribute speaker { text }
delivery = attribute delivery { "spoken" | "sung" }
action = attribute action { text }
# 
# Line content
line =
  element line {
    mixed { (chara | place)* }
  }
#  elements have a kind attribute with values like building, nature, etc.
#  elements have a ref attribute that contains a standardized character name
# The ref value is defined as text, rather or-group fixed values, to accomodate other shows 
place = element place { kind, text }
kind = attribute kind { text }
chara = element chara { ref, text }
ref = attribute ref { text }

Discussion

The schema tries to use self-documenting names and explanatory comments wherever possible, but here are a few additional details:

Repetition in metadata: For the metadata section, whether you made items repeatable depends on what you expect XML documents of the same type to look like. For our sample schema above we thought of each song in this type of corpus as having exactly two <title> elements, one for the show title and one for the song title, so it was important to allow more than one, which we did with a plus sign. The model above is really too loose, though, for two related reasons: 1) it allows multiple titles of the same type and 2) it allows titles of only one type and none of the other type. It also allows the types of titles to appear in any order, which may not matter to XML processing, but if different songs put their titles in different orders it introduces cognitive friction that can compromise the developer’s focus. In Real Life we would use a tighter model, requiring exactly two titles (not the looser one or more) and requiring them in a specific order. That might look like:

metadata = element metadata { show_title, song_title, characters, artist, source }
show_title = element title { show_title_type, text }
song_title = element title { song_title_type, text }
show_title_type = attribute type { "musical" }
song_title_type = attribute type { "song"} 

With this revision the content model for <metadata> requires exactly two titles, one of each type, and in a specific order. Because the <title> elements have different values for the type attribute, we use different labels (show_title, song_title), both of which describes elements of type <title> but with different attribute labels (show_title_type, song_title_type). Those attribute labels both describe attributes with the name type but with different single, specific string values.

This revision is stricter, which is an advantage, since it prevents us from having more than two <title> elements, it requires both song and musical titles, and it requires that the two, which are distinguished by the value of their type attributes, occur in a specific order. At the same time, it’s more difficult to read because of the indirection, that is, because we have to read through several schema lines to discover that each of the two type attributes has a single allowed value. The specificity of this part of the model makes this a good opportunity to insert a bit of Russian doll Relax NG syntax into our schema:

metadata = element metadata { show_title, song_title, characters, artist, source }
show_title = element title {
    attribute type { "musical" },
    text
}
song_title = element title {
    attribute type { "song" },
    text
}

With Russian doll notation, we don’t use labels for the attributes on the two types of titles inside the content models. What we do instead is define the type attribute right inside the content model for the element that uses it. We don’t recommend Russian doll notation in general because deeper nesting becomes difficult to read, but here we find that because of the simplicity of the attribute declarations the schema becomes clearer if we define them in place. Your mileage may vary, so any of the models above are acceptable, but in Real Life we would use this last one.

As for the artist, you may have allowed more than one, thinking maybe that different songs would be arranged by different people, or because you want to include composer, lyricist, arranger, and perhaps others. Our sample schema, above, assumed that one person was responsible for all of these creative roles, and if our corpus consisted of songs from this show we’d leave it as that, so that’s what we’ve done here. If you anticipate using your schema with other shows that may have different persons in different artistic roles, it would be better to make <artist> repeatable. Note that we’ve used a comment to document the assumption that dictated our specific schema rule.

Attribute values as or-groups of strings: In our solution we chose to write out some attribute values as or-groups of strings so that we could constrain them to one of two or three options (for example, the value of the attribute tone can be "positive", "negative", or "neutral", but it has to be one of those three exact strings). Whether to specify a value as an or-group of strings or, more loosely, with the keyword text, depends on whether we can anticipate all possible values in advance, and we hardcoded values only for items where that was the case. Since for the delivery attribute we assumed that there were two types of line delivery in a musical, "spoken" or "sung", we represented that as an or-group of strings, as well. On the other hand, the ref attribute of the chara element is left open because there are many characters in this musical besides the three or four mentioned in the text and we anticipate using the same schema to validate those other songs. For the same reason we define the speaker attribute as text, since Natalya and Rach aren’t the only characters who sing in the musical. As long as the inventory of possibilities is finite (and not insanely long) it would not be a mistake to use an or-group of strings that lists all of the character names in the show, but that would limit the schema to this one show. If you want to be able to use the same schema for any musical, the list of possible characters becomes infinite, and therefore not enumerable, so text becomes the only option.

Whether you hardcoded specific string values or left them open by using the keyword text, it is always best to leave a comment in your schema explaining why, as we do above.

Common issues

Flexibility: The element <direction> indicates a stage direction, which will not always appear at the beginning of the lyrics section, and there’s no reason there couldn’t be multiple stage directions within a song. Putting it in a schema without attaching a repetition indicator and without allowing some flexibility to its location risks limiting the schema to just this song.

Empty elements: The element <toneshift/> is an empty element. Empty elements can be represented in two ways that are syntactically different but have exactly the same meaning:

<toneshift/> is a self-closing empty-element tag. Note the slash at the end. This notation does not use separate start- and end-tags; the single self-closing tag represents the entire element. Empty elements have no content (nothing between start- and end-tags, which is why they can get away with just a single tag). They may have attributes, although <toneshift> doesn’t.

<toneshift></toneshift> is a combination of a regular start-tag followed by regular end-tag with nothing between them.

These notations mean exactly the same thing, but we prefer using the self-closing empty-element single-tag version because it is more self-documenting and easier to understand at a glance.

The HTML specification recommends using the single-tag notation only for elements that must always be empty and the combination of start- and end-tag with nothing between them for elements that could have content in principle but happen not to in a particular location. That recommendation is not part of XML, where the two notations are exactly synonmous and can be used in exactly the same locations.

Content models: Whatever is listed in the content model of an element is only its attributes plus whatever (elements or text) is directly between its start- and end-tags, that is, its children but not its deeper descendants. For example, if you have a <song> element that contains a <stanza> element that, in turn, contains lines, you wouldn’t model the <song> as:

song = element song { stanza+, line+ } # Note: bad code

because <song> doesn’t have any child <line> child elements (although it does have <line> descendants).

Answer Key: XML Test

Instructions

Answer the following questions and upload your answers to Canvas. All tests in this course are open book, so you can look things up and you can try out your code in <oXygen/>, but you cannot receive help from another person.

Create your answers in <oXygen/> as a plain-text document, which you can do by creating a new document (using the File → New menu options) and typing text into the Type filter text box. Do not use a word processor (like Microsoft Word) because word processors do things like changing your straight quotation marks to curly ones, which you don’t want. The file you upload must follow our file-naming conventions, using .txt as the filename extension (to indicate that you are submitting a plain-text file).

Questions

Question:The following is an example of an XML document. What is the name of the root element of this example?

  sugar
  butter
  flour
  chocolate chips

Answer: The root element, or the element that encloses all other elements in the document, is <ingredients>. A well-formed document must have exactly one root element.

Question: What is the difference between descriptive markup and presentational markup? Give an example of each type and explain 1) why the descriptive markup is descriptive, 2) why the presentational markup is presentational, and 3) why we recommend using descriptive markup in digital humanities projects.

Answer:

Descriptive markup focuses on the role and meaning of an element in its context, while presentational markup focuses on the rendered appearance of an element.

A piece of italicized text might be used in a text to represent the thoughts of a character, and descriptive markup might tag that piece as <thought> to represent its meaning to the story. Meanwhile, presentational markup might simply tag that piece as <italic>.

We prioritize descriptive markup in digital humanities work because there are more types of meaning in the world than types of appearance, which means a computer can derive the appearance from the meaning more reliably than if it has to to derive the meaning from the appearance.

Question: Which of the following scenarios would cause a well-formedness error (red square) in an XML document? (Some may be poor style because they’re confusing, while still being well-formed, and the task is to identify only the ones that are not well-formed.) For each example that is not well-formed, explain why they are not well-formed and how you might fix them.

Answers listed under each scenario

An element in the document does not contain any content, e.g.:

<bookmark></bookmark>

Answer: Empty elements are allowed in XML, so this does not raise a well-formedness error.

A speech is tagged as having two speakers, e.g.:

<speech speaker="homer" speaker="bart">Doh!</speech>.

Answer: An element can only have one attribute with a given name, so having two attributes called speaker is a well-formedness violation. The most robust way to fix this is to combine the speaker names under a single attribute, e.g., .

Some of you may have tried . This is well formed and it received full credit on this test, but for reasons we’ll explore later, it is not as useful an approach as the one we suggest above.

Duplicating the tag and its content to create two separate <speech> tags (i.e., Doh! Doh!) will produce a well-formed document, but isn’t informationally correct because it creates two speeches where only one existed in the source document. In this example, it would make it appear as though each character independently said D’oh, one after the other, rather than saying it in unison, which is what the original version tries to express. If you want to use two separate elements, there are strategies for representing the simultaneity with attributes (along the lines described in the answer to 3H, below).

Removing one of the speaker attributes/values would create a well-formed document, but that’s not a useful strategy because it loses information. If, for example, you were to delete speaker="homer" you would get a green square at the expense of not knowing, when you perform analysis later, that Homer spoke here.

A comment occurs inside an element, e.g.:

     
    As I do live, my honoured lord, 'tis true;
    And we did think it writ down in our duty
    To let you know of it.

Answer: Comments can go nearly anywhere in an XML document, including inside elements. This would not raise a well-formedness error.

An attribute name (in this case, main speaker) contains a space character, e.g.:

    If it be,
    Why seems it so particular with thee?

Answer: An attribute name cannot contain a space, since a space would cause <oXygen/> to see the two words as separate attribute names (in this case main, with no attribute value, which is itself a well-formedness error, and speaker). This could be fixed by combining the two-word name in several ways, such as snake case (e.g., main_speaker), kebab case (e.g., main-speaker), and camel case (e.g., mainSpeaker).

An attribute value contains a space character, e.g.:

    If it be,
    Why seems it so particular with thee?

Answer: An attribute value can contain a space, since the content of the value is a literal string, and not the name of an XML element or attribute. This will not raise a well-formedness error.

Paired start- and end-tags differ in capitalization:

    If it be,
    Why seems it so particular with thee?

Answer: Start- and end-tags must be exactly the same, including capitalization, because XML is case-sensitive, so an element called <line> is a completely different type of element than one called <Line>. This error can be fixed by making the start- and end-tags agree exactly in the spelling of the element name, e.g., … .

Most XML taggers prefer lower-case element names, so although … is also well-formed (and receives full credit on this test), we recommend standardizing on the lower-case spelling instead.

A complete document lacks a single root node, e.g.:

 
Curly
Larry
Moe

Answer: All XML documents must have a root element that contains all other elements. This well-formedness error can be fixed by wrapping everything but the XML declaration (which is not document content and which is allowed only as the absolute first line of the file) in a root element (in this case something like <stooges>).

An element contains a less-than sign:

1 < 2

Answer: Since a less-than sign (<) is the symbol used for opening a tag, <oXygen/> thinks that it must be followed immediately by an element name, optional attribute information, and then by a greater-than sign. Since the character immediately after the less-than sign in this example is a space and element names cannot contain space characters, and also because there is no following greater-than sign, this raises a well-formedness error.

You can fix this by replacing the reserved character with an appropriate character entity, which an XML processor will understand correctly as representing a literal character that could not be entered directly because it has a special meaning. The character entity that represents < is &lt; (the lt is a mnemonic for less than). See the Entities and numerical character references section of our XML tutorial for discussion and examples.

Alternatively, you could replace the < symbol with its corresponding numerical charaacter reference (or NCR) in Unicode; this works much like the character entities mentioned above, but with a Unicode value in place of the mnemonic. The NCR for < is &#60; (decimal) or &#x3c; (hex). We prefer the character entity because it is easier for a human to recognize and understand.

An element contains a greater-than sign:

2 > 1

Answer: This will not raise a well-formedness error because although the greater-than sign represents the end of a tag, it has that special markup meaning only if it has been preceded by a less-than sign. Since that isn’t the case here, an XML processor, such as <oXygen/>, understands that it has a literal meaning and does not raise an error.

There is a character entity for the greater-than sign, which is spelled &gt;, and it is not incorrect to use it, although we struggle to think of a situation where it is required to avoid having a greater-than sign mistaken for a tag end-delimiter.

An element (in this case <quote>) starts in one context and ends in another (in this case, two different <line> elements), e.g.:

    And all should cry, Beware! Beware!
    His flashing eyes, his floating hair!
    Weave a circle round him thrice,
    And close your eyes with holy dread,
    For he on honey-dew hath fed
    And drunk the milk of Paradise.

Answer: Elements must start and end in the same context (that is, inside the same parent element). There are a few ways to resolve this error, each of which involves compromises, and the simplest may be to tag separately each of the quote pieces inside each <line> element. This isn’t fully satisfactory by itself because the lines do not actually contain separate quotes (for example, this strategy wouldn’t let us count quotes in the text by counting <quote> elements), and you can adjust for that by adding an attribute that shows which <quote> elements go together. For example, if you tag all parts of the same quote as <quote group="a">, XML processing can use the shared attribute value a to know that these constitute a single textual quote. We’ll introduce other methods later in the course.

Just putting the <quote> tags around the last two words of the first line gets a green square, but it isn’t an adequate remedy because it changes the meaning of the document by failing to say that the following lines are also quoted text.

The markup languages community refers to the issues involved in this example as overlap and discontinuity. The overlap involves quotes and lines that overlap one another, and the discontinuity involves tagging the quote components separately even though they are really parts of a single quote. XML was designed to represent hierarchy well, and it does, but that benefit comes at the expense of not being able to represent overlap or discontinuity in a way that feels natural to humans.

We might think that if XML didn’t prohibit overlap the problem would go away, but the issue is that the prohibition against overlap is there for a reason: that’s what enables a computer to recognize XML as a hierarchy. Computers can navigate and process hierarchies more easily than overlapping or discontinuous structures, and, for better or for worse, the designers of XML decided to commit to hierarchy and accept the inconveniences that come with that commitment.

Regex Test

The task

Your task is to describe how you would use regular expressions to mark up a plain-text document (see below). There are usually alternative ways to complete that sort of task, and your approach does not have to match ours as long as it 1) makes reasonable use of regular expressions to avoid unnecessary manual tagging, 2) tags as many parts of the document structure as you can sensibly tag by using regular expression matching, and 3) produces well-formed XML (possibly with a bit of manual cleanup). Well-formed XML is a baseline requirement in Real Life, and is therefore worth a lot of points on this test. You do not have to add the sort of analytic markup that requires primarily manual tagging.

The document you’ll tag for this test is the first two chapters of Bram Stoker’s

Dracula

, which you can access at dracula.txt. We have extracted these chapters from the Project Gutenberg publication of the 1897 New York edition, but all you need for the text is our two chapters, so you don’t have to consult anything on the Gutenberg site unless you’re just eager to read more of the story. The italicized phrase Mem. is short for memorandum, that is, Jonathan’s reminder, as a note to himself within his diary, about a detail that requires follow-up. The lines that consist entirely of asterisks and space characters have a structural function that you’ll have to identify, by looking at the contexts in which they appear, in order to decide how that function should be reflected in your XML.

Things to tag (in whatever order makes sense for you; some may require a bit of manual intervention):

The entire document

The document title

Chapters

Chapter labels (e.g., CHAPTER I), chapter titles, chapter subtitles ((_Kept in shorthand._) in Chapter 1)

Dated diary entries (each chapter contains three of these, and the dated diary entries contain the paragraphs)

The date and place information at the beginning of a dated entry (e.g., 5 May. The Castle.; only some contain places). You can tag these just as a single element

5 May. The Castle.

or, for extra credit, tag them as a group but also tag the date part and the place part separately inside them:

    5 May.
    The Castle.

Paragraphs

Italics (surrounded by underscores; if you can identify the reason for the italics, e.g., foreign word or emphasis, tag descriptively; otherwise tag presentationally)

Note: You might be tempted to autotag quotations by matching a pair of quotation marks plus whatever is between them, but that will run into trouble because this document uses a common older typographic convention where quotations that extend for more than one paragraph have an open quotation mark at the beginning of each paragraph but a closing quotation mark only after the last one, which means that the quotation marks are not paired. Here’s an example:

He went, but immediately returned with a letter:--

"My Friend.--Welcome to the Carpathians. I am anxiously expecting you. Sleep well to-night. At three to-morrow the diligence will start for Bukovina; a place on it is kept for you. At the Borgo Pass my carriage will await you and will bring you to me. I trust that your journey from London has been a happy one, and that you will enjoy your stay in my beautiful land.

"Your friend,

"DRACULA."

For this test you may leave the quotation marks as they are in the original and not remove them and replace them with markup.

Optional bonus task

You’re welcome to stop here, but if you’d like more practice: If we were undertaking this task in Real Life we would create a schema to validate our XML. Because the sort of regex-supported tagging we use is not XML-aware, it is possible to create XML that is not well formed and that is tagged inconsistently. <oXygen/> will always check XML for well-formedness, but we would use a schema to ensure that our markup consistently says what we want it say. If you’d like, then, create a schema that models what your document analysis tells you about the structure of the document and verify that your markup is valid against the schema.

What to submit

Write up the process you follow in a markdown document (following our file-naming conventions and with an .md filename extension) as a sequence of steps. Inline code snippets must be surrounded in backticks because that’s how markdown formats code snippets, and, for the same reason, code blocks must be fenced, that is, surrounded by triple backticks on separate lines. You can remind yourself about markdown syntax at the GitHub three-minute guide to Mastering markdown that you read earlier. Your markdown must distinguish the individual steps clearly, and it must also format your code snippets and code blocks clearly and correctly. Be sure to check how it looks in the formatted view, and not just the editing view where you type.

In your list of steps be sure to indicate clearly when you use the Dot matches all option. If you don’t say explicitly that you’re using it for a particular step, we’ll assume that it is unchecked for that step. You might want to create a little template for each step in your process that includes 1) match pattern, 2) replacement, 3) whether or not you checked Dot matches all, and 4) a bit of prose that explains what each step does, as well as anything else that seems necessary to explain why you are doing what you’re doing at a particular moment.

Submit just the markdown document—not the XML it produces. We will follow your instructions step by step to replicate your method and recreate your tagged XML ourselves. If you create the optional bonus Relax NG schema, submit that, as well.

Feel free to ask questions in Slack (there are #regex and #markdown channels, and the #general channel for anything that doesn’t fit in any more specific one). We can’t tell you how to do something, but if you’re stuck on a particular detail we’ll be happy to do what we can to point you in the right direction without just telling you the answer.

XSLT Test

Background

Andrew Lang and his wife, Leonora (Nora) Blanche Alleyne, were the editors of a late Victorian collection of twelve colored books of fairy tales. These volumes were enormously influential in reshaping the cult of fairy tales (originally a type of folk and literary text for adults) into a genre of children’s literature.

The Yellow Fairy Book

was first published in 1894.

The task

Your task is to write XSLT that will create an XHTML reading view of our XML version of

The Yellow Fairy Book

, which can be found at yellowFairy.xml. The look and style of the output is up to you except for places where we specify (below) certain elements to include, and with the exception of those features, any valid XHTML output that is consistent with the way a collection of tales might reasonably be rendered is fine.

You may find it helpful to download and explore the Relax NG schema that we used to validate the XML, which you can find at http://dh.obdurodon.org/yellowFairy.rnc. You can develop and run your XSLT transformation without the schema, but examining the schema might help you understand the structure of the XML, which could make it easier to plan your transformation.

We’ve also used a Schematron schema to validate some aspects of our XML. You can ignore that for now, and we’ll learn how to work with Schematron—and why it will be useful for your projects—later in the semester, but you’re welcome to take a look now if you’re curious.

You should upload both your XSLT and the XHTML output created by your transformation. If you undertake the extra-credit CSS option (see below), upload your CSS file, as well.

General guidelines

Perform a sanity check after each step in your development: Does your output look the way you expect in a browser? Does the angle-bracketed output look the way you expect in <oXygen/>?

Validate your XHTML output before you submit it. Valid output is a baseline requirement for any XSLT transformation, and for that reason it is worth a lot of points on this test. To ensure that your document is valid, save the output of your transformation, open it in <oXygen/>, and validate it there. Your document must conform to the type of valid HTML5 with XML syntax that you’ve been using consistently in other assignments and in your projects. It must include the correct HTML doctype declaration, it must be in the correct HTML namespace, and it must make appropriate descriptive use of HTML elements. For example, use headers hierarchically (e.g., don’t skip from <h1> to <h3>), use a meaningful and appropriate @alt attribute on all <img> elements, etc.

Avoid hard-coding information into your XSLT that is available from the XML. For example, don’t type out titles that are present in the XML, don’t require a specific number of stories, etc.

There are multiple ways to complete this task, and your solution doesn’t have to be the same as ours. With that said, your XSLT must be consistent with good practice. For example, apply templates to all stories at once instead of to each one separately, don’t confuse XPath patterns with XPath expressions, don’t use pull processing (<xsl:for-each>, <xsl:value-of>) where push processing (<xsl:apply-templates> and <xsl:template>) would be more appropriate, etc.

Organize your XSLT in a way that makes sense and include comments (comments in XSLT use the same syntax as in XML) that label sections of your code and help you find your way around. Comments should not be This is My XSLT Test; make them insightful not only to help you during your coding process, but also to help those who will view your code (think of your hypothetical project teammates were this part of your course project). Good use of mindful comments is worth points!

Should you have any questions, please ask in the #xslt channel in our Slack workspace. We can’t give you the answer, but we’ll do whatever we can short of that to help. Should you get stuck at a particular point in your XSLT in a way that doesn’t get cleared up over Slack, include a properly formatted comment that tells us specifically how you tried to debug it, where by specifically we mean what (exactly) you tried, what you expected, what you got instead, what you think the source of the problem is, how you tried to fix it, etc. Not being able to get all the way to a solution can nonetheless earn credit, but only if you provide a thoughtful and specific description of your debugging efforts.

Required tasks

At a minimum, the output of your transformation must include the following features that might be expected in any reading view of a book containing a collection of tales:

A main title as well as author and editor names that are extracted from the XML (not typed in as literal values). The title should appear in two places: in a

element inside the and in an

inside the

.

A table of contents with the story names.

Each story in its own HTML <section> with the story name at the start (extracted from the XML, and not supplied as a literal value).

Story titles and the content (if present) formatted in a way that stands out from the rest of the text.

All paragraphs within each chapter so that your stories retain their original paragraphed structure and are not rendered as single blocks of continuous text.

Bonus (optional, extra-credit) tasks

Style your HTML meaningfully with CSS that enhances the overall effect of the reading view. Your CSS must be in a separate file, which you should upload to Canvas along with your XSLT and HTML, and it must be linked to the HTML output of your transformation with an HTML <link> element that you create as part of your transformation. Make sure that the filename of your CSS matches the filename specified in the @href attribute on your <link> element.

Enhance the table of contents to create clickable links that scroll the page to the appropriate location within the main text.

The tales in this collection originate with different authors and storytellers, and the element is used to denote when someone other than just Andrew Lang or Nora Alleyne contributed to a story. Instead of rendering that information where it appears in the XML, create footnotes with raised numbers after the title within the body and put the sources (that is, the contents of the <origin> element) at the end of the entire page, with clickable links that connect them. The HTML for raised numbers is <sup> (mnemonic: superscript).

You’ll need to generate the note numbers programmatically and they need to run consecutively, so that the first note number is 1, the second is 2, etc.